agriculture.gov.au 2019-06-26

# Department of Agriculture Privacy policy - Department of Agriculture and Water Resources

​​​​​​​​​​​​​​​​​​​​The department provides the following Privacy Policy in accordance with the _Privacy Act 1988_.

## Co​mple​​te privacy policy  

Department of Agriculture, March 2014

### Download

If you have difficulty accessing these files, please visit web accessibility.

## Condensed privacy policy

Department of Agriculture, March 2014

### Download

If you have difficulty accessing these files, please visit web accessibility.

### Online version

#### ​​About this policy 

The purpose of this privacy policy is to:

  * clearly communicate the personal information handling practices of the Department of Agriculture and Water Resources
  * enhance the transparency of the department’s operations, and
  * give individuals a better and more complete understanding of the sort of personal information the department holds, and the way we handle that information.

This condensed privacy policy ​has been developed to follow the ‘layered policy’ format, which means that it offers layers of greater or lesser detail so people can read as much as they wish and find what they need. This document provides you with a succinct overview of how we handle your personal information. Our complete privacy policy​​ can be accessed on our website.

If you wish to make any comments or suggestions about the privacy policy, you can do so by contacting the privacy team in the Office of the General Counsel within the department via:

Email: [Privacy](mailto:privacy@agriculture.gov.au)  
Phone: (02) 6272 3933  
Mail: Privacy, Department of Agriculture and Water Resources, PO Box 858, Canberra ACT 2601.

Any comments and/or suggestions will be reviewed and considered by the department’s privacy officers.

If you would like to request the privacy policy be made available in an alternate format or language, such as for the vision impaired, or for those from non-english speaking backgrounds, please also contact the privacy team. Reasonable steps will be taken to provide alternate access.

This privacy policy is reviewed and updated annually. Changes will be advertised via the ‘Latest News’ window on the department’s website.

The privacy policy was last reviewed in March 2014.

#### Our obligations under the Privacy Act

This privacy policy sets out how we comply with our obligations under the [ Priva​cy Act 1988](https://www.legislation.gov.au/Series/C2004A03712) (Privacy Act). As an Australian Government agency, we are bound by the Australian Privacy Principles (APP) in the Privacy Act which regulate how government agencies collect, use, store and disclose personal information, and how individuals may access and correct personal information held about them.

##### Personal information

Personal information is defined in s 6(1) of the Privacy Act as ‘information or an opinion about an identified individual, or an individual who is reasonably identifiable:

  * whether the information or opinion is true or not, and
  * whether the information or opinion is recorded in a material form or not’.

What constitutes personal information will vary, depending on whether an individual can be identified or is reasonably identifiable in the particular circumstances. For example, personal information could include:

  * a name or address
  * bank account details
  * photos or videos
  * information about an individual’s mannerisms, their opinions or where they work.

Note: information does not have to include an individual’s name to be personal information. For example, in some cases, a date of birth and post code may be enough to identify a person.

##### Sensitive information

Sensitive information is a subset of personal information with additional requirements under the Privacy Act.

Sensitive information is defined in the Privacy Act as information or an opinion about an individual’s racial or ethnic origin, political opinions, membership of a political association, religious beliefs or affiliations, philosophical beliefs, membership of a professional or trade association, membership of a trade union, sexual preferences or practices, or criminal record that is also personal information; health information about an individual, genetic information about an individual, biometric information that is to be used for the purpose of automated biometric verification/identification and biometric templates.

#### The kinds of personal information collected and held by the department

The department collects and holds a variety of personal information, as included in the table below.

Information Type| Description  
---|---  
Personal information| 

  * name
  * age and gender
  * contact details (including address, phone and email addresses)
  * bank account details
  * photos, videos or audio of individuals
  * employment details (including occupation, qualifications, CV and remuneration)
  * education details (level of education, study assistance and courses)
  * financial information (ABN)

Sensitive information  
(a subset of Personal information)| 

  * racial or ethnic origin
  * political opinion or association
  * religious beliefs or affiliations
  * philosophical beliefs
  * trade or professional associations and memberships
  * union membership
  * criminal record
  * health or genetic information

#### How the department collects and holds your personal information

##### How the department collects your personal information

When the department collects personal information about you, in the majority of cases, we will collect this information directly from you. However, there may be times where the department may collect personal information from your agent or a third party. If this occurs, such collection will be in accordance with the APPs.

#### The purposes for which the department collects, holds, uses and discloses your personal information

The purpose for the department collecting your personal information is important as it restricts how the department can use and disclose your personal information, unless an exception in the Privacy Act applies. Unless an exception applies, the department will:

  * only use or disclose your personal information for the purpose it was collected, and
  * notify you of this purpose at the time of collection, or as soon as practicable after collection.

The department will only use or disclose your personal information for another purpose where it is able to do so in accordance with the Privacy Act.

There are a number of general purposes for which the department may collect, hold, use and disclose your personal information.

#### How to access and seek correction of your personal information

Individuals have a right to request access to their personal information and to request its correction if it is inaccurate, out of date, incomplete, irrelevant or misleading.

If you are an external client or stakeholder you should contact the relevant business area within the department, in writing, for access to or correction of your personal information. For example, applicants for a grant program should first contact the program administrator via email or letter. If you do not know which area of the department holds your personal information you can contact the department’s switch on 02 6272 3933. Alternatively, you can use the ‘contact us’ link on the department’s website.

Current and former departmental employees who wish to gain access to, or correct their personal information need to contact the People Services Branch (HR Assist) in the first instance. HR Assist can be contacted on 02 6272 3933 or via email at [HRAssist](mailto:HRAssist@agriculture.gov.au).

#### How you can complain about the treatment of your personal information and how the complaint will be handled

You can make a complaint if you believe the department has breached the APPs or mishandled your personal information.

Privacy breaches can be caused by a variety of factors, affect different types of personal information and give rise to a range of actual or potential harm to individuals, agencies and organisations. Consequently, there is no single way of responding to a privacy breach. Each breach will need to be dealt with on a case-by-case basis. All complaints and alleged breaches will be investigated by a privacy officer and the complainant will be advised of the outcome.

The department’s privacy officers will investigate:

  * concerns that the personal information contained in a record of a client, stakeholder or departmental officer has been mishandled
  * any complaints and/or allegations about a breach of the APPs, and
  * all privacy-related matters referred from the Privacy Commissioner within the Office of the Australian Information Commissioner (OAIC).

In the first instance, any privacy concerns or complaints should be reported to the department’s privacy team. This can be done by:

Phone: 02 6272 3933  
Email: [Privacy](mailto:privacy@agriculture.gov.au)  
Mail: Privacy, Department of Agriculture and Water Resources, PO BOX 858, Canberra ACT 2601.

If you are unhappy with the department’s response or reply, you also have the option of contacting the Privacy Commissioner within the OAIC. The Privacy Commissioner can be contacted on:

Phone: 1300 363 992  
Email: [Enquiries](mailto:enquiries@oaic.gov.au)  
Mail: OAIC, GPO Box 5218 Sydney NSW 2001.

This site adheres to Commonwealth Government Internet security standards, including the Defence Signals Directorate guidelines.

**Note:** There is an inherent risk associated with the use of an insecure public network such as the World Wide Web. A user's transactions (including emails) may be viewed, intercepted, corrupted or modified by, or otherwise disclosed to, a third party. The Commonwealth cannot guarantee the security or integrity of any transaction over such a network, including personal or other private information transmitted via email to or from a Department email address (X@agriculture.gov.au). The Commonwealth is not liable in connection with the transmission of any such information (including as a result of negligence).

If you prefer to use an alternative means of delivery, you can send the information via the department's normal communications methods; i.e. mail, phone or fax. If you take this approac​h, please make it clear which part of the website you are responding to.

### Information collected through our website and online services

A variety of information is collected by using the department’s website and online services. Some of this may be personal information, which is summarised in the table below:

Information type| Treatment  
---|---  
**Emails and electronic forms**| 

The department’s servers may record your email address if you send us a message online. Your email address will not be added to a mailing list unless you have provided it to the department in order to subscribe to one of our subscription services.

When you send us a message online the department’s servers may also record your usage data in the form of page URLs that you have visited on our websites. These URLs will be used for research purposes only within the department.​

Where you choose to send the department a completed electronic form that includes your personal details, the department collects personal information such as name, address and email address. The information collected by email or electronic forms will be used only for the purpose for which you provided it, unless an exception applies.

For those who do not wish to use the internet to transmit information, the department provides alternative ways of providing information. For example, forms may be printed (or obtained in hard copy) and lodged by post.  
  
**Payment information**| 

If you choose to pay for a service or product using secure credit card payment facilities available on our website, you will be asked to provide your credit card details. Credit card details are encrypted from the moment they are entered into an electronic form. All other information entered into an electronic form will be encrypted upon submission to the department. 

The department stores encrypted credit card details only until the industry standard charge back period has expired (currently 10 months).  
  
**Clickstream data**| 

The department makes a record of your visit to the website and logs the following information for statistical purposes: the user's Internet Protocol (IP) address, the date and time of the visit to the site, the web pages accessed and documents downloaded, the previous site visited, and the user's web browser and operating system.  
  
**Google Analytics**| 

In addition to web server logs, the department’s website also uses Google Analytics, a web analytics service provided by Google Incorporated (Google). Reports obtained from Google Analytics are used to help improve the department’s website. Google Analytics uses 'cookies' to help analyse how users use the site.

The information generated by the cookie about your use of the website (including your IP address) will be transmitted to and stored by Google on servers in the United States of America. Google will use this information for the purpose of evaluating your use of our website, compiling reports on website activity for website operators and providing other services relating to website activity and internet usage. Google may transfer this information to third parties where required to do so by law, or where such third parties process the information on Google's behalf. Google will not associate your IP address with any other data held by Google.

By using the department’s website, you consent to the processing of data about you by Google in the manner and for the purposes set out above. Please refer to [Google's privacy policy](http://www.google.com/privacy.html) for further information.  
  
**Cookies**| 

The department utilises cookies when you visit our site. A cookie is a piece of information that a website sends to your browser when you access information at a site. Cookies give websites a sense of memory, allowing them to recognise one user from another. Most sites use them to do anything from counting the number of viewers they have, delivering tailored editorial content, or enabling website editors to identify which of their pages are most popular. 

Despite common myths, the cookies sent to your PC cannot read your hard drive, obtain any information from your browser or command your computer to perform any action. They are designed so that they cannot be sent to, or be retrieved by, any other site. Upon receipt of the information from the Department of Agriculture and Water Resources site your browser also saves a Department of Agriculture and Water Resources cookie on your hard-disk. Each time you use your computer to access the Department of Agriculture and Water Resources website, the information that was previously received is sent back to the Department of Agriculture site and Water Resources by your browser, this enables us to identify the information that is most important to you and ensure it can be located effectively. Most commonly used browsers support the use of cookies.

You may refuse the use of cookies by selecting the appropriate settings on your browser, however please note that if you do this you may not be able to use the full functionality of some websites. For more information about cookies and instructions on how to adjust your browser settings to restrict or disable cookies, see the [Office of the P​rivacy Commissioner website](https://www.oaic.gov.au/) or the [Interactive Advertising Bureau website](http://www.allaboutcookies.org/).  
  
## ​​Privacy Impact Assessment Register

This register includes Privacy Impact Assessments ( **PIA** ) in accordance with the [Privacy (Australian Government Agencies — Governance) APP Code 2017](https://www.legislation.gov.au/Details/F2017L01396).

Date

| 

Title   
  
---|---  
20 May 2019| Bulk mail and survey functions  
6 May 2019|  NEXDOC/Enhanced Exports Traceability  
1 Apr 2019| FMIS/Technology One  
25 Sep 2018| Levy Payer Register  

11 Jul 2018

| 

Internal Staff Policy  
  
​​​​​
